<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Polyclimate</title>
<link>https://polyclimate.org/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://polyclimate.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 08:45:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>New Scenarios</title>
  <dc:creator>Robert Gieseke</dc:creator>
  <link>https://polyclimate.org/posts/new-scenarios/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div id="fig-sketches" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-sketch-scenariomip" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/new-scenarios/scenariomip-workshop-report-fig-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-sketches"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(a) Figure 1 from <span class="citation" data-cites="vanVuuren_2023_gsqcbg">Vuuren et al. (2023)</span> (CC-BY)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-sketch-gmd" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/new-scenarios/gmd-2023-176-2a.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-sketches"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(b) Figure 2a from <span class="citation" data-cites="meinshausenPerspectiveNextGeneration2023">Meinshausen et al. (2023)</span> (CC-BY)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: Illustrative emission pathway sketches in <span class="citation" data-cites="vanVuuren_2023_gsqcbg">Vuuren et al. (2023)</span> and <span class="citation" data-cites="meinshausenPerspectiveNextGeneration2023">Meinshausen et al. (2023)</span></figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Last week a new paper and a new preprint on scenario creation and their assessment were published. First, a group effort with 41 co-authors: <em>A perspective on the next generation of Earth system model scenarios: towards representative emission pathways (REPs)</em> <span class="citation" data-cites="meinshausenPerspectiveNextGeneration2023">(Meinshausen et al. 2023)</span>. It’s open for review comments in GMD. The social media comments I saw so far where quite mixed. Some were apparently seeing this as a community split and invited to join the ScenarioMIP process, while the paper itself presents itself as a contribution to the ScenarioMIP effort.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The initial June 2023 workshop discussions for the forthcoming ScenarioMIP protocol, at which this paper’s proposal was presented, also picks up some elements of this convergence of views (Figure 1 in van Vuuren et al., 2023).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(p.&nbsp;25)</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Further considerations beyond those outlined here may inform the ongoing efforts of pathway design as part of CMIP, including ScenarioMIP (van Vuuren et al., 2023) and/or other model intercomparison projects (MIPs). We hope that our perspective can serve as an input into a strategic approach for driving ESMs with policy-relevant futures in this critical and contribute to further community reflections 805 on the next generation of framing pathways that we think will greatly benefit from an open and inclusive discussion given the far-reaching consequences for climate science and policy stemming from the scenario design.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(p.&nbsp;31/32)</p>
<p>Given that I started <a href="https://polyclimate.org/posts/announcing-project-polyclimate/">Polyclimate</a> as a place to think about how (some parts of) climate science could be done more in the open and collaboratively I find these discussions quite fascinating and look forward to a future study which analyses the social and political processes behind the scenario development.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>This paper has no official mandate. Doesn’t mean it’s not relevant but it’s not the CMIP endorsed activity.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/PFriedling/status/1700181854438019578">Pierre Friedlingstein on Twitter</a></p>
<p>It’s often hard to get review comments<sup>1</sup>, but the naming of their proposed scenarios is definitely something that will lead to comments. Whether there are emissions pathways that can be ruled out is still up for debate.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“World Avoided” is a misleading name, which overstates progress in reducing emissions.</p>
<p>If RCP 8.5 was never plausible then it’s only a world avoided in scenario modelers’ imaginations.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/DoctorVive/status/1700243779897155753">Genevieve Guenther on Twitter</a></p>
<p>Others were excited about both the “hypothetical” loss and damage scenario with emisssions reductions having started in 2015 and the high emissions scenarios.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>These two parallels universes: I want to know EVERYTHING about them</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/ketanjoshi.co/post/3k6scqm5nm525">Ketan Joshi on Bluesky</a></p>
<p>There is a a lot of literature which tries to assign historical emissions responsibility and the loss and damage debate will certainly be important in the next climate negotiations.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I love the idea of a ‘what might have been’ scenario. So much of climate change has been politicians saying “Well, this all happened well before our tenure”, so it would be great to have something to point to and say “see how much less messed up it could have been if you’d done your jobs”.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/willemh.bsky.social/post/3k6seexqjqu25">Willem Huiskamp on Bluesky</a></p>
<p>An important question then is of course how such a hypothetical scenario would look. 5% emissions reductions from 2015? 10%?</p>
<p>Also interesting to note that a sketch in in the ScenarioMIP workshop report <span class="citation" data-cites="vanVuuren_2023_gsqcbg">(Vuuren et al. 2023)</span> has a question mark pathway in the area between ‘continued’ emissions and a below-2°C pathway, an area which is left empty in the REP sketch, see Figure&nbsp;1. The selection, design and naming of scenarios has many implications and there is not much time if things are to be ready for the second Global Stocktake in 2028.</p>
<div id="fig-gmd-3" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/new-scenarios/gmd-2023-176.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: Potential timelines discussed in Fig. 3 of <span class="citation" data-cites="meinshausenPerspectiveNextGeneration2023">Meinshausen et al. (2023)</span> (CC-BY)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Given the discussions on timelines and cut-off dates Figure&nbsp;2 for scenarios and their assessment feeding into the second Global Stocktake via a yet unknown AR7 product another paper published last week is also quite relevant: <em>AR6 scenarios database: an assessment of current practices and future recommendations</em> <span class="citation" data-cites="petersAR6ScenariosDatabase2023">(Peters et al. 2023)</span>.</p>
<p>A critical assessment of the mitigation scenarios assessed in WG3 of the IPCC it calls for a “A new generation mitigation scenarios database” and for having the scenarios assessment be public during the assessment process instead of only after the final report publication.</p>
<div id="fig-peters-ar6-projects" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/new-scenarios/peters-ar6-projects.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;3: Number of vetted scenarios from each project, (CC-BY <a href="https://twitter.com/Peters_Glen">@peters_glen</a>)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>From a description of the current process, an analysis of skewness in the distribution of submitted scenarios (dominated by a small number of models and projects, see Figure&nbsp;3) it makes several proposals. Quoting from a thread on Twitter<sup>2</sup>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<ul>
<li>A more active community in shaping research questions (e.g., not within closed EU projects)</li>
<li>Shifting towards open &amp; peer-reviewed scenario protocols, to solicit more diverse feedback &amp; submissions</li>
<li>A focus on openness, transparency, inclusion</li>
<li>A living scenario database (instead of closed until publication as in the IPCC). Annual publications, like <a href="https://twitter.com/gcarbonproject">@gcarbonproject</a> , could routinely maintain, update, &amp; assess the database.</li>
<li>Encourage the community to assess the database, not let the IPCC authors do it alone</li>
<li>A strong institutional foundation is important, but a diversity of voices representing users &amp; different modelling approaches &amp; paradigms is essentials</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/Peters_Glen/status/1699732964689477892">(Glen Peters on Twitter)</a></p>
<p>For the proposal of a living scenario database I believe the ingredients are already there. With the fantastic <em>climate-assessment</em> package <span class="citation" data-cites="kikstraIPCCSixthAssessment2022a">Kikstra et al. (2022)</span> have open-sourced the core climate assessment engine. A future living scenario database could built on this and be developed in the open on GitHub, along future improvements and updates to the assessment pipeline. With a total size of less than 350 MB for the global scenarios<sup>3</sup> the database could fit well below into the recommended limits of a GitHub repository of 1GB so there might be no need to maintain an actual database. If needed it could also be split up into sub-projects.</p>
<p>Several approaches could be possible, for example submitting scenarios via Pull Requests to a central scenario DB repository, the assessment being handled by an automated pipeline using GitHub Actions writing back the results to the repository. A distributed, local approach might be another possibility, if the computing demands are to high to be handled by (free tier) GitHub Actions.</p>
<p>Scenario developers would then have to run the pipeline locally and submit not only their input data but also the harmonized emissions and climate assessment to a central repository database. This approach might even be better for scenario developers (or done locally before submission anyways) and avoid surprises like re-classification due to infilling and harmonization. For example, they might have thought they submitted a below 1.5 scenario, but filling in emissions not covered in their model could push it into an overshoot one. During submission via Pull Requests automated checks could be performed like they are done in the current submission portal. Ideally, the submitted scenarios would directly be rendered into visualizations and be explorable on a website. Archiving could happen through the Zenodo integration with GitHub, so there would always be a citable reference of the latest version.</p>
<p>Lots of possibilities and not much time. Leave your thoughts and comments below!</p>





<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-kikstraIPCCSixthAssessment2022a" class="csl-entry">
Kikstra, Jarmo S., Zebedee R. J. Nicholls, Christopher J. Smith, Jared Lewis, Robin D. Lamboll, Edward Byers, Marit Sandstad, et al. 2022. <span>“The <span>IPCC Sixth Assessment Report WGIII</span> Climate Assessment of Mitigation Pathways: From Emissions to Global Temperatures.”</span> <em>Geoscientific Model Development</em> 15 (24): 9075–9109. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-15-9075-2022">https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-15-9075-2022</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-meinshausenPerspectiveNextGeneration2023" class="csl-entry">
Meinshausen, Malte, Carl-Friedrich Schleussner, Kathleen Beyer, Greg Bodeker, Olivier Boucher, Josep G. Canadell, John S. Daniel, et al. 2023. <span>“A Perspective on the Next Generation of <span>Earth</span> System Model Scenarios: Towards Representative Emission Pathways (<span>REPs</span>).”</span> <em>Geoscientific Model Development Discussions</em>, September, 1–40. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-2023-176">https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-2023-176</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-petersAR6ScenariosDatabase2023" class="csl-entry">
Peters, Glen P., Alaa Al Khourdajie, Ida Sognnaes, and Benjamin M. Sanderson. 2023. <span>“<span>AR6</span> Scenarios Database: An Assessment of Current Practices and Future Recommendations.”</span> <em>Npj Climate Action</em> 2 (1, 1): 1–6. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s44168-023-00050-9">https://doi.org/10.1038/s44168-023-00050-9</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-vanVuuren_2023_gsqcbg" class="csl-entry">
Vuuren, D. van, C. Tebaldi, B. C O’Neill, ScenarioMIP SSC, and Workshop Participants. 2023. <span>“ScenarioMIP Workshop: Pathway to Next Generation Scenarios for CMIP7.”</span> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.8186116">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.8186116</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Leave your thoughts and comments below!↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>If the URL still says Twitter, I can still call the network Twitter, right?↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>AR6_Scenarios_Database_World_v1.1.csv and AR6_Scenarios_Database_metadata_indicators_v1.1.xlsx↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Polyclimate</category>
  <category>Scenarios</category>
  <guid>https://polyclimate.org/posts/new-scenarios/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 08:45:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://polyclimate.org/posts/new-scenarios/gmd-2023-176-2a.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="121" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Polyclimate Global Projections</title>
  <dc:creator>Robert Gieseke</dc:creator>
  <link>https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-global-projections/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>In 2015 the legally binding <a href="https://unfccc.int/sites/default/files/resource/docs/2015/cop21/eng/10a01.pdf">Paris Agreement</a> included the overarching goals of holding</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“the increase in the global average temperature to well below 2 °C above pre-industrial levels and pursuing efforts to limit the temperature increase to 1.5 °C above pre-industrial levels, recognizing that this would significantly reduce the risks and impacts of climate change”.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The question of which temperature level will be reached when is thus crucial. There exist a number of projects, reports from international organizations, as well as research papers aiming to answer the question what level of global temperature rise will be reached at the end of the century or how big the gap to scenarios consistent with temperature targets is. This is done under consideration of pledges and Nationally Determined Contributions (NDCs) of countries or analyzing currently implemented or planned policies, for example:</p>
<ul>
<li>the <a href="https://www.unep.org/resources/emissions-gap-report-2022">UNEP Emissions Gap Reporte</a> reports,</li>
<li>the <a href="https://climateactiontracker.org/">Climate Action Tracker</a>,</li>
<li>assessments published by the UNFCCC as <a href="https://unfccc.int/process-and-meetings/the-paris-agreement/nationally-determined-contributions-ndcs/ndc-synthesis-report/ndc-synthesis-report">NDC synthesis reports</a>, or</li>
<li>the <a href="https://www.iea.org/reports/world-energy-outlook-2022">IEA</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>The Remaining Carbon Budget approach is another widely used metric to track the progress, or rather non-progress, in keeping below the agreed temperature limits. It is most often reported as <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?n"> years remaining until the budget is used up and often depicted as a countdown clock, by media and research institutes alike.</p>
<div id="fig-carbon-budgets" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-carbon-budget-mcc" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-global-projections/mcc-countdown-clock.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-carbon-budgets"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(a) MCC Countdown Clock <a href="https://www.mcc-berlin.net/fileadmin/data/clock/carbon_clock.htm">(Screenshot from mcc-berlin.net)</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-carbon-budget-taz" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-global-projections/taz-carbon-budget.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-carbon-budgets"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(b) taz Countdown Clock <a href="https://taz.de/Neue-CO2-Uhr-auf-tazde/!5810221/">(Screenshot from taz.de)</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-carbon-budget-igcc" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-global-projections/climate-change-tracker-budget.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-carbon-budgets"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(c) IGCC/Climate Change Tracker <a href="https://climatechangetracker.org/igcc/current-remaining-carbon-budget-and-trajectory-till-exhaustion">(Screenshot from climatechangetracker.org)</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: Carbon Budget Visualizations</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>While the Budget approach is liked by NGOs and activists as it can be used to clearly define the remaining shares of countries, cities, or sectors and is also used in legislation, for example in the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/guidance/carbon-budgets">UK Carbon Budgets</a>, it has been criticized a lot. Changes in input or reference data, uncertainties in the climate response, and definitional issues have led Glen Peters to ask in <em>Beyond carbon budgets</em> whether the</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“carbon budget concept has perhaps served its purpose, time is short. To enact policy, a carbon budget is woefully too simplified.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="petersCarbonBudgets2018">(Peters 2018)</span></p>
<p>Fully reproducible Remaining Carbon Budgets, which are required to disentangle the differences between reported budgets, have only recently become available, see for example <span class="citation" data-cites="nichollsImplicationsNonlinearitiesCumulative2020">(Nicholls et al. 2020)</span> and the <a href="https://github.com/Rlamboll/AR6CarbonBudgetCalc">AR6 Carbon Budget Calculations on GitHub</a>.</p>
<p>Despite efforts to improve the understanding and comparability of the Remaining Carbon Budget approach there remains confusion when updates are published. Recently, the <a href="https://www.igcc.earth/">Indicators of Global Climate Change</a> initiative included an update of the AR6 WGI budget, which shortened the time until the budget will be used up by about two years. Some media adopted their online trackers, for example the German daily <em>taz</em> (Figure&nbsp;1 (b)), which before used the numbers based on the IPCC report from MCC (Figure&nbsp;1 (a)). The IGCC dashboard (see Figure&nbsp;1 (c)) includes a slider for the likelihood to stay under 1.5 °C and makes the implied assumption of future CO₂ emissions transparent, which is another communication challenge.</p>
<p>Probably not obvious to most people discussing the Carbon Budget, but mentioned in the Climate Change Tracker explanation text and in the IGCC paper is that the year of the budget being exhausted is not necessarily the year when 1.5 °C is reached.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Note that the 50 % RCB is expected to be exhausted a few years before the 1.5 °C global warming level is reached due to the way it factors future warming from non-CO2 emissions into its estimate.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="forsterIndicatorsGlobalClimate2023">(Forster et al. 2023)</span></p>
<p>For a deeper discussion of the <em>Opportunities and challenges in using remaining carbon budgets to guide climate policy</em> see also <span class="citation" data-cites="matthewsOpportunitiesChallengesUsing2020">Matthews et al. (2020)</span>.</p>
<p>In contrast to the short term and rapidly shrinking Remaining Carbon Budgets are the assessments which report being on a pathway to <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?n.m"> °C at the end of the century. Often a distinction is made between pathways based on implemented policies, NDC pledges, or optimistic assumptions of full implementation of all net zero targets.</p>
<p>The Climate Action Tracker is currently reporting 2.7 °C as its headline number for 2100, based on policies and actions, see Figure&nbsp;2.</p>
<div id="fig-cat" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-cat-thermometer" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-global-projections/CAT_2022-11_Graph_Thermometer_4Bars_Annotatio.width-1110.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-cat"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(a) <a href="https://climateactiontracker.org/global/cat-thermometer/">CAT Thermometer</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-cat-temperatures" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-global-projections/CAT_2022-11_Graph_2100WarmingProjection.width-1110.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-cat"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(b) <a href="https://climateactiontracker.org/global/temperatures/">CAT 2100 Warming Projections</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: Climate Action Tracker assessment, November 2022 © 2009-2023 by Climate Analytics and NewClimate Institute</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The 2022 <a href="https://www.unep.org/resources/emissions-gap-report-2022">UNEP Gap Report</a> has 2.8°C with policies currently in place and the 2022 <a href="https://unfccc.int/documents/619180">UNFCC NDC Synthesis Report</a> summarizes:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>” The best estimate of peak temperature in the twenty-first century (projected mostly for 2100 when temperature continues to rise) is in the range of 2.1–2.9 °C depending on the underlying assumptions.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Most of these assessments don’t report the question when 1.5 or 2.0 °C will be reached. Underlying are a number of assumptions, especially for the extension until 2100 and its dependency on the underlying scenario databases. This makes it difficult to compare different assessments, for a detailed discussion see for example <span class="citation" data-cites="jefferyMeasuringSuccessImproving2018">Jeffery et al. (2018)</span> and <span class="citation" data-cites="gutschowExtendingNearTermEmissions2018">Gütschow et al. (2018)</span>. An overview of recent studies can be found in this 2022 <a href="https://data.climateresource.com.au/ndc/20221110-briefing/2022_Briefing_WarmingImplicationsNDCs_ClimateResource_FINAL.pdf">briefing paper</a> from Climate Resource.</p>
<p>The public discourse is thus dominated by either a rapidly being used up budget (sometimes communicated with a faux accuracy of hundredths of seconds) or by a being on a rather deterministic sounding <em>pathway</em> to a temperature in 2100, when, using average global life expectancy, everybody currently alive and their children won’t be around anymore.</p>
<p>I think that a different approach could amend these perspectives and be less reliant on scenario databases and their sometimes opaque assumptions on technologies or negative emissions. One could construct stylized scenarios, constant emissions, reductions or further increase in emissions and run these in the same way as scenarios based on NDCs or policies. The results could then be reported as follows:</p>
<p><em>If we reduce emissions by n% per year, 1.5 °C will be reached between 20xx and 20yy.</em></p>
<p><em>If emissions plateau for n years, we will reach a level of 1.5 °C in x years.</em></p>
<p><em>If emissions keep rising at n% per year, the 2.0 °C limit will be breached between 20xx and 20yy.</em></p>
<p>Aggregated NDCs could also be included, for example first follow an NDC trajectory and then decline or plateau.</p>
<p>As a proof of concept I used the excellent <a href="https://climate-assessment.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">climate-assessment</a> package, used in the IPCC WG3 scenario assessment <span class="citation" data-cites="kikstraIPCCSixthAssessment2022a">(Kikstra et al. 2022)</span>. For testing the approach I constructed three basic scenarios with the main greenhouse gases. Starting from the historical emissions used in the <em>climate-assessment</em> package I extended them with the change rates as reported in the IGCC emissions update <span class="citation" data-cites="forsterIndicatorsGlobalClimate2023">(Forster et al. 2023)</span>. Next to a ‘persistence’ scenario with constant emissions, a continuous 5% reduction and 1% increase were considered as illustrative examples. Remaining greenhouse gases beyond CO₂, CH₄, N₂O, and other inputs and disaggregation of F-gases were infilled using <a href="https://silicone.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">Silicone</a> as included in the <em>climate-assessment</em> workflow.</p>
<p>Figure&nbsp;3 shows the stylized scenarios and their temperature response for the median and 33rd to 66th percentile range using the <a href="https://docs.fairmodel.net/en/latest/">FaIR</a> climate model.</p>
<div id="fig-scenario" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-scenario-minus-5" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-global-projections/minus-5.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-scenario"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(a) Stylized scenario with 5% reductions</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-scenario-persistence" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-global-projections/persistence.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-scenario"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(b) Stylized scenario with constant emissions</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-scenario-plus-1" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-global-projections/plus-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-scenario"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(c) Stylized scenario with 1% increase</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;3: Examples of stylized scenarios and their temperature response.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This is of course only illustrative, many aspects need further thought and exploration:</p>
<ul>
<li>2022 (or soon 2023) emissions could also be used as a starting point,</li>
<li>instead of percent reductions, one could use a more complex function to account for “hard-to-abate” and negative emissions (see discussion on Robbie Andrew’s <a href="https://folk.universitetetioslo.no/roberan/t/global_mitigation_curves.shtml">figure of the mitigation challenge</a>) or a simple linear pathway</li>
<li>one could use specific lower bounds and reduction rates for different species</li>
<li>all climate models available in <em>climate-assessment</em> or <a href="https://openscm-runner.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">OpenSCM</a> should be used</li>
<li>the question of updates of historical emissions and (re-)calibration</li>
</ul>
<p>In general such a framework can also be used to analyze trade-offs between reduction rates for different species, like CO₂, CH₄, or F-Gases.</p>
<p>In the example above I used the automatic infilling which is also something that needs further research. For the highly stylized scenarios it could make sense to extend all inputs in the same way or to use some other relationship from the literature or modelling. See Figure&nbsp;4 for some examples of infilled inputs.</p>
<div id="fig-infill" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-infill-sulfur" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-global-projections/sulfur.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-infill"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(a) Infilled sulfur emissions</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-infill-sf6" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-global-projections/sf6.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-infill"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(b) Infilled SF6 emissions</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;4: Infilled inputs for the stylized scenarios above.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In any case, making such an assessment requires the collaboration and inputs from many researchers, a number of tools and datesets. This makes it perfect to become project <strong>Polyclimate1</strong>. I believe it could provide a useful addition to existing global projections and potentially be communicated more easily. A repository with the proof-of-concept notebooks used for creating and running the scenarios is available on <a href="https://github.com/polyclimate/polyclimate1">GitHub</a>.</p>
<p>Leave your thought and comments below!</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-forsterIndicatorsGlobalClimate2023" class="csl-entry">
Forster, Piers M., Christopher J. Smith, Tristram Walsh, William F. Lamb, Robin Lamboll, Mathias Hauser, Aurélien Ribes, et al. 2023. <span>“Indicators of <span>Global Climate Change</span> 2022: Annual Update of Large-Scale Indicators of the State of the Climate System and Human Influence.”</span> <em>Earth System Science Data</em> 15 (6): 2295–2327. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-15-2295-2023">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-15-2295-2023</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-gutschowExtendingNearTermEmissions2018" class="csl-entry">
Gütschow, Johannes, Mairi Louise Jeffery, Michiel Schaeffer, and Bill Hare. 2018. <span>“Extending <span>Near-Term Emissions Scenarios</span> to <span>Assess Warming Implications</span> of <span>Paris Agreement NDCs</span>.”</span> <em>Earth’s Future</em> 6 (9): 1242–59. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/2017EF000781">https://doi.org/10.1002/2017EF000781</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-jefferyMeasuringSuccessImproving2018" class="csl-entry">
Jeffery, M. Louise, Johannes Gütschow, Marcia R. Rocha, and Robert Gieseke. 2018. <span>“Measuring <span>Success</span>: <span>Improving Assessments</span> of <span>Aggregate Greenhouse Gas Emissions Reduction Goals</span>.”</span> <em>Earth’s Future</em> 6 (9): 1260–74. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2018EF000865">https://doi.org/10.1029/2018EF000865</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-kikstraIPCCSixthAssessment2022a" class="csl-entry">
Kikstra, Jarmo S., Zebedee R. J. Nicholls, Christopher J. Smith, Jared Lewis, Robin D. Lamboll, Edward Byers, Marit Sandstad, et al. 2022. <span>“The <span>IPCC Sixth Assessment Report WGIII</span> Climate Assessment of Mitigation Pathways: From Emissions to Global Temperatures.”</span> <em>Geoscientific Model Development</em> 15 (24): 9075–9109. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-15-9075-2022">https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-15-9075-2022</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-matthewsOpportunitiesChallengesUsing2020" class="csl-entry">
Matthews, H. Damon, Katarzyna B. Tokarska, Zebedee R. J. Nicholls, Joeri Rogelj, Josep G. Canadell, Pierre Friedlingstein, Thomas L. Frölicher, et al. 2020. <span>“Opportunities and Challenges in Using Remaining Carbon Budgets to Guide Climate Policy.”</span> <em>Nature Geoscience</em> 13 (12, 12): 769–79. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-020-00663-3">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-020-00663-3</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-nichollsImplicationsNonlinearitiesCumulative2020" class="csl-entry">
Nicholls, Z. R. J., R. Gieseke, J. Lewis, A. Nauels, and M. Meinshausen. 2020. <span>“Implications of Non-Linearities Between Cumulative <span>CO2</span> Emissions and <span class="nocase">CO2-induced</span> Warming for Assessing the Remaining Carbon Budget.”</span> <em>Environmental Research Letters</em> 15 (7): 074017. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/ab83af">https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/ab83af</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-petersCarbonBudgets2018" class="csl-entry">
Peters, Glen P. 2018. <span>“Beyond Carbon Budgets.”</span> <em>Nature Geoscience</em> 11 (6, 6): 378–80. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-018-0142-4">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-018-0142-4</a>.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Polyclimate</category>
  <category>Polyclimate1</category>
  <category>Global Projections</category>
  <guid>https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-global-projections/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2023 10:20:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-global-projections/persistence.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="60" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Polyclimate Emissions</title>
  <dc:creator>Robert Gieseke</dc:creator>
  <link>https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-emissions/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div id="cell-fig-global-emissions" class="cell" data-execution_count="2">
<details>
<summary>Code</summary>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-overflow-wrap code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">import</span> pandas <span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">as</span> pd</span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">import</span> matplotlib.pyplot <span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">as</span> plt</span>
<span id="cb1-3"></span>
<span id="cb1-4">plt.style.use(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"ggplot"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-5"></span>
<span id="cb1-6">cat_df <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> pd.read_excel(</span>
<span id="cb1-7">    <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"https://climateactiontracker.org/documents/1131/CAT_2022_Warming_projections_global_update.xlsx"</span>, </span>
<span id="cb1-8">    sheet_name<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Global Emissions time series"</span></span>
<span id="cb1-9">)</span>
<span id="cb1-10"></span>
<span id="cb1-11">cat <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> pd.DataFrame(cat_df.iloc[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">23</span>, <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">3</span>:].values, index<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span>cat_df.iloc[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">13</span>, <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">3</span>:].astype(<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>)).dropna()</span>
<span id="cb1-12">cat.columns <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> [<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"CAT"</span>]</span>
<span id="cb1-13"></span>
<span id="cb1-14">ipcc <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> pd.read_excel(</span>
<span id="cb1-15">    <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"https://open-data.metadata.works/ipcc/437/ipcc_ar6_figure_spm_1_archive.xlsx?response-content-disposition=attachment"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-16">    sheet_name<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"panel_a"</span></span>
<span id="cb1-17">)</span>
<span id="cb1-18">ipcc <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> ipcc.groupby(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"year (panel_a)"</span>).<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sum</span>()</span>
<span id="cb1-19">ipcc.index.name <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"year"</span></span>
<span id="cb1-20">ipcc <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> ipcc.iloc[:, <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>]</span>
<span id="cb1-21"></span>
<span id="cb1-22">igcc <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> pd.read_csv(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"https://github.com/ClimateIndicator/GHG-Emissions-Assessment/raw/main/results/ghg_emissions_co2e.csv"</span>, index_col<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-23"></span>
<span id="cb1-24">fig, ax <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> plt.subplots()</span>
<span id="cb1-25">ipcc.plot(ax<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span>ax)</span>
<span id="cb1-26">igcc.loc[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1990</span>:, :].iloc[:, <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>:].<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sum</span>(axis<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>).plot(ax<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span>ax)</span>
<span id="cb1-27">cat.plot(ax<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span>ax, legend<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">False</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-28">ax.legend([<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"IPCC (Apr. 2022)"</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"IGCC (Jun. 2023)"</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"CAT (Nov. 2022)"</span>], loc<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"lower right"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-29">ax.set_xlabel(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">""</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-30">ax.set_ylabel(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Gt CO₂-eq / yr"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-31">ax.set_title(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Global Emissions (using different source datasets)"</span>)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span></code></pre></div>
</details>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div id="fig-global-emissions" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-emissions/index_files/figure-html/fig-global-emissions-output-1.png" width="587" height="433" class="figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: Global emission estimates from <a href="https://ipcc-browser.ipcc-data.org/browser/dataset?id=437">IPCC AR6 WGIII SPM</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-15-2295-2023">IGCC (2023)</a>, and <a href="https://climateactiontracker.org/global/temperatures/">CAT (2022)</a>, each using different sources</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>It might appear surprising but there exists no complete and regularly updated global emissions dataset which covers the greenhouse gases needed to run a simple climate model or to answer the question what are global emissions levels currently at with confidence. Usually, each time a new combination of source datasets has to be assembled. Depending on approach the values might differ significantly.</p>
<p>IPCC AR6 WGIII reported 59 Gt CO₂-eq in 2019, the <em>Indicators of Global Climate Change 2022</em> paper <span class="citation" data-cites="Forster_2023_gsbsj4">(Forster et al. 2023)</span> used some different data sources and updated landuse data and reported 55 Gt CO₂-eq. The <a href="https://climateactiontracker.org/global/temperatures/">Climate Action Tracker</a> had 52.3 Gt CO₂-eq for 2019 in its November 2022 update.</p>
<p>Some of the differences can be explained by different choice of dataset but the decision which dataset to use sometimes appear arbitrary. In the <em>Indicators of Global Climate Change 2022</em> paper, an update to the data published in the IPCC’s AR6 report, the authors pick different data sources:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>We also use the same type of data sources but make important changes to the specific selection of data sources to further improve the quality of the data, as suggested in the knowledge gap discussion of the WGIII report (Dhakal et al., 2022). Instead of using EDGAR data (which are now available as version 7), we use GCB data for CO2-FFI, PRIMAP-hist data for CH4 and N2O, and atmospheric concentrations with best-estimate lifetimes for UNFCCC F-gas emissions (Hodnebrog et al., 2020). As in AR6 WGIII we use GCB for net CO2-LULUCF emissions, taking the average of three bookkeeping models.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Forster_2023_gsbsj4">(Forster et al. 2023)</span></p>
<p>They give the reason for their choices as follows:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>There are three reasons for these specific data choices. First, national greenhouse gas emissions inventories tend to use improved, higher-tier methods for estimating emissions fluxes than global inventories such as EDGAR or CEDS (Dhakal et al., 2022; Minx et al., 2021). As GCB and PRIMAP-hist integrate the most recent national inventory submissions to the UNFCCC, selecting these databases makes best use of country-level improvements in data-gathering infrastructures.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Forster_2023_gsbsj4">(Forster et al. 2023)</span></p>
<p>If the suggestion to use more data from national inventories can be inferred from the <em>Knowledge Gaps</em> section in the IPCC WGIII Chapter 2 discussion, why wasn’t it already used in AR6? The data sources used in the IGCC report were available then as well.</p>
<p>Given the number of datasets there are other combinations possible. A recent paper on <em>National contributions to climate change due to historical emissions</em>, with quite some overlap of authors with the IGCC paper, prefers third-party reported data which lie in the middle of other estimates:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>As discussed above, Minx et al.&nbsp;(ref. 64) compared available estimates of CH4 and N2O emissions and found that PRIMAP-hist (TP scenario) lies centrally amongst those estimates. […] Hence, we note that the CH4 and N2O emissions estimates used in the current study lie centrally within a large uncertainty range globally and within a poorly constrained uncertainty range on national scales.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Jones_2023_gsc84q">(Jones et al. 2023)</span></p>
<p>In any case, more discussion and research is needed, as was discussed in the <a href="https://essd.copernicus.org/articles/15/2295/2023/essd-15-2295-2023-discussion.html#CC11">peer review</a> of the IGCC paper.</p>
<p>Different choices have also been made in previous IPCC reports. AR4 wrote in its chapter on <a href="https://archive.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg3/en/ch1s1-3.html">“Energy, emissions and trends in Research and Development – are we on track?”</a> that</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>[a] variety of sources exist for determining global and regional GHG and other climate forcing agent trends. Each source has its strengths and weaknesses and uncertainties.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>For its assessment it appears to have used EDGAR and CDIAC. Then, AR5 used versions of <a href="https://www.iea.org/data-and-statistics/data-product/greenhouse-gas-emissions-from-energy">IEA</a> and <a href="https://edgar.jrc.ec.europa.eu/">EDGAR</a> data <span class="citation" data-cites="krey2014annex">(Krey et al. 2014)</span>.</p>
<p>It is hard to disentangle changes over time and to understand differences between studies if different datasets are used every time. The detailed review of CO₂ datasets by <span class="citation" data-cites="andrewComparisonEstimatesGlobal2020">Andrew (2020b)</span> found that differences between datasets to a large part come down to different system boundaries, the inclusion or omission of sources. It also included a call for an Intercomparison Project:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Given the inconsistent system boundaries across emissions datasets, one could conceive of a “carbon emissions dataset intercomparison project”, or CEDIP, along the lines of the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP) and other related model comparison projects. A core part of these intercomparison projects is the requirement that participants report model outputs to a specified and very clear template such that the issue of system boundary differences is removed. For example, an estimate for global total CO2 emissions could not be reported for a dataset if it excluded sources or countries. In effect, a CEDIP would extend the work done in this article, allowing each data provider to submit according to their superior understanding of their own datasets, permitting more robust comparison, and, critically, allowing lessons to be gained such that estimates can be improved.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the reply to Reviewer #1 Robbie Andrew wrote:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Page 40 line 637: Would a recommendation to data producers be to make their methodology and data sources more transparent to allow for better understanding?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The difficulty I have here is what concrete suggestions can be made for doing this. I know that different groups have thought a lot about how to transparently and comprehensively document methods and sources, but still we come up with a lot of missing and obscured information. <strong>I tend to think this is almost unsolvable</strong>. While it might be thought that the best approach might be to have a standard format, the methods differ quite substantially such that it’s not necessarily straightforward to report them in the same way.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Andrew_2020_gsmw4p">(emphasis mine, Andrew 2020a)</span></p>
<p>Getting data providers to agree on a common format is definitely a challenge and releasing or cleaning up data pipelines is not a priority for researchers in the current academic system.</p>
<p>Another issue is the interdependence of datasets, which makes it hard to assess uncertainty from differences between datasets. From the same study the construction and relationships of CO₂ emissions datasets is shown below.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-emissions/essd-12-1437-2020-f01-web.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure 1 from <span class="citation" data-cites="andrewComparisonEstimatesGlobal2020">Andrew (2020b)</span> shows interrelation and build-up of different CO₂ datasets, see original study for detailed caption (<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC-BY</a>)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="community-projects" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="community-projects">Community projects</h3>
<p>There exist a number of emissions data projects who already have elements of community projects. Even open peer review and working in public can improve the process and signal openness to outside contributors.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://globalcarbonbudget.org/">Global Carbon Budget</a>, an annually published report which is part of the <a href="https://www.globalcarbonproject.org">Global Carbon Project</a> is something to look into when thinking on how to produce datasets from the community <span class="citation" data-cites="friedlingsteinGlobalCarbonBudget2022a">(Friedlingstein et al. 2022)</span>. While there are many co-authors collaborating only a small number is directly working on fossil and land-use emissions, as other area of the Carbon Cycle are also covered in the paper. In any case, the lack of direct funding has been a persistent problem:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The work we do in <a href="https://twitter.com/gcarbonproject/">@gcarbonproject</a> has <em>zero</em> direct funding, we have to align with other project activities to cover costs. Yet, we persist in updating annually.</p>
<p>These seem to be standard issues for anyone working on data.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/Peters_Glen/status/1446381946913894404">(Glen Peters on Twitter)</a></p>
<p>The Global Carbon Budget is widely used, but covers only CO₂. The <a href="https://primap.org/primap-hist/">PRIMAP-hist</a> dataset covers all Kyoto greenhouse gases <span class="citation" data-cites="gutschowPRIMAPhistNationalHistorical2016b">(Gütschow et al. 2016)</span> but doesn’t include emissions from international aviation and shipping. Emissions from land-use are not included in the main file but only in a separate file and come with a caveat since “they are constructed from different sources using different methodologies and are not harmonized” <span class="citation" data-cites="Guetschow_2023_gsmrpq">(Gütschow and Pflüger 2023)</span>.<br>
In a comment on the <a href="https://polyclimate.org/posts/announcing-project-polyclimate/">announcement post</a> <a href="https://github.com/mikapfl">Mika Pflüger</a> mentioned the potentially collaborative setup for doing the hard work of freeing data submitted to the UN from PDFs and the challenges with storing larger data on GitHub. Code and data can be found in their <a href="https://gin.hemio.de/jguetschow/UNFCCC_non-AnnexI_data">GIN server</a>.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.pnnl.gov/projects/ceds">Community Emissions Data System (CEDS)</a> for Historical Emissions <span class="citation" data-cites="Hoesly_2018_gcxtgm">(Hoesly et al. 2018)</span> covers a different subset of species and is probably the most open of the emission products . The <a href="https://github.com/JGCRI/CEDS/">code on GitHub</a> is available and only some input data from the IEA is missing to make this fully reproducible. However, long-term sustainability has been a question as well from Reviewer #1:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>An outline of long-term plans for the CEDS database is needed in the summary section to build confidence in its sustainability. Modelers would like to know if they can rely on the CEDS system working even after CMIP6. What are the plans for maintenance of the back-end software, frequency of updates to the input data and for maintaining funding for CEDS?</p>
</blockquote>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Anonymous_2017_gsm2zg">(Anonymous 2017)</span></p>
<p>The <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20191219040122/http://www.match-info.net/">MATCH</a> (Ad-hoc group for the modelling and assessment of contributions to climate change) working group is quite interesting in this context. As part of UNFCCC negotiations Brazil proposed in 1997</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>to set differentiated emissions reduction targets for Parties according to the impact of their historic emissions on temperature rise (document FCCC/AGBM/1997/MISC.1/Add.3).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>From the expert meetings an open group of voluntary contributors emerged, who published several papers, including assessments of historical emissions, supported by governments who funded travel and administrative support. It could be instructive to learn more from the history of this project (and how to prevent results getting lost when domains aren’t renewed anymore.)</p>
<p>What are the challenges for having an emissions dataset intercomparison project? Have any proposals already be written? How can we get a regularly updated dataset of the inputs required to run a simple climate model? Do we need something like the Global Carbon Project for all greenhouse gases?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>We have put a lot of effort into understanding the variation in fossil CO₂ emissions, but what about other GHG emissions?</p>
<p>I would say we have some work to do… We need a <a href="https://twitter.com/gcarbonproject">@gcarbonproject</a> covering all GHG emissions! https://essd.copernicus.org/articles/13/5213/2021/</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/Peters_Glen/status/1459065929124376577">(Glen Peters on Twitter)</a></p>
<p>And do we have to rely on crowdfunding to get it?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Yes please. Not having one single authoritative dataset for non-CO2 emissions makes running an emissions-based simple climate model particularly difficult🙃</p>
<p>Will donate $10 to a crowdfunder?</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/chrisroadmap/status/1459156819285352496">(Chris Smith on Twitter)</a></p>
<p>Leave your thoughts and ideas in the comments!</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-Andrew_2020_gsmw4p" class="csl-entry">
Andrew, Robbie. 2020a. <span>“Responses to Reviews.”</span> Copernicus <span>GmbH</span>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-2020-34-ac1">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-2020-34-ac1</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-andrewComparisonEstimatesGlobal2020" class="csl-entry">
———. 2020b. <span>“A Comparison of Estimates of Global Carbon Dioxide Emissions from Fossil Carbon Sources.”</span> <em>Earth System Science Data</em> 12 (2): 1437–65. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-12-1437-2020">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-12-1437-2020</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Anonymous_2017_gsm2zg" class="csl-entry">
Anonymous. 2017. <span>“Review of Hoesly Et Al for Publication in <span>ACP</span>,”</span> April. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-2017-43-rc1">https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-2017-43-rc1</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Forster_2023_gsbsj4" class="csl-entry">
Forster, Piers M., Christopher J. Smith, Tristram Walsh, William F. Lamb, Robin Lamboll, Mathias Hauser, Aurélien Ribes, et al. 2023. <span>“Indicators of Global Climate Change 2022: Annual Update of Large-Scale Indicators of the State of the Climate System and Human Influence.”</span> <em>Earth System Science Data</em> 15 (6): 2295–2327. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-15-2295-2023">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-15-2295-2023</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-friedlingsteinGlobalCarbonBudget2022a" class="csl-entry">
Friedlingstein, Pierre, Michael O’Sullivan, Matthew W. Jones, Robbie M. Andrew, Luke Gregor, Judith Hauck, Corinne Le Quéré, et al. 2022. <span>“Global <span>Carbon Budget</span> 2022.”</span> <em>Earth System Science Data</em> 14 (11): 4811–4900. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-14-4811-2022">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-14-4811-2022</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-gutschowPRIMAPhistNationalHistorical2016b" class="csl-entry">
Gütschow, Johannes, M. Louise Jeffery, Robert Gieseke, Ronja Gebel, David Stevens, Mario Krapp, and Marcia Rocha. 2016. <span>“The <span class="nocase">PRIMAP-hist</span> National Historical Emissions Time Series.”</span> <em>Earth System Science Data</em> 8 (2): 571–603. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-8-571-2016">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-8-571-2016</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Guetschow_2023_gsmrpq" class="csl-entry">
Gütschow, Johannes, and Mika Pflüger. 2023. <span>“The PRIMAP-Hist National Historical Emissions Time Series (1750-2021) V2.4.2.”</span> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.7727475">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.7727475</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Hoesly_2018_gcxtgm" class="csl-entry">
Hoesly, Rachel M., Steven J. Smith, Leyang Feng, Zbigniew Klimont, Greet Janssens-Maenhout, Tyler Pitkanen, Jonathan J. Seibert, et al. 2018. <span>“Historical (1750<span></span>2014) Anthropogenic Emissions of Reactive Gases and Aerosols from the Community Emissions Data System (<span>CEDS</span>).”</span> <em>Geoscientific Model Development</em> 11 (1): 369–408. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-11-369-2018">https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-11-369-2018</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Jones_2023_gsc84q" class="csl-entry">
Jones, Matthew W., Glen P. Peters, Thomas Gasser, Robbie M. Andrew, Clemens Schwingshackl, Johannes Gütschow, Richard A. Houghton, Pierre Friedlingstein, Julia Pongratz, and Corinne Le Quéré. 2023. <span>“National Contributions to Climate Change Due to Historical Emissions of Carbon Dioxide, Methane, and Nitrous Oxide Since 1850.”</span> <em>Scientific Data</em> 10 (1). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-023-02041-1">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-023-02041-1</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-krey2014annex" class="csl-entry">
Krey, Volker, Omar Masera, Geoffrey Blanford, Thomas Bruckner, Roger Cooke, Karen Fisher-Vanden, Helmut Haberl, et al. 2014. <span>“Annex 2-Metrics and Methodology.”</span>
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Polyclimate</category>
  <category>Emissions</category>
  <guid>https://polyclimate.org/posts/polyclimate-emissions/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 09:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Announcing Project Polyclimate</title>
  <dc:creator>Robert Gieseke</dc:creator>
  <link>https://polyclimate.org/posts/announcing-project-polyclimate/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://polyclimate.org/posts/announcing-project-polyclimate/duck.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="Cover of Michael Nielsen's book Reinventing Discovery, a tree and three ducks in the background"></p>
<p>It is 100 days until <a href="https://www.cop28.com/en/">COP28</a> in Dubai. The <a href="https://unfccc.int/topics/global-stocktake">Global Stocktake</a>, the process to assess progress towards the goals of the Paris Climate Change Agreement, is scheduled to take place every five years and for the first time during COP28.</p>
<p>Some questions and indicators one might ask about during such a Global Stocktake, or in fact constantly, when thinking about climate change, could be:</p>
<ul>
<li>What are global emissions levels?</li>
<li>How far are we from 1.5 or 2.0°C?</li>
<li>How big is the remaining carbon budget?</li>
<li>When adding together climate plans of countries (<a href="https://unfccc.int/NDCREG">NDCs</a>), where do we end up?</li>
</ul>
<p>When trying to look up an answer for questions like these, they can be surprisingly difficult to find given their importance for our common future. Of course answers exist, in academic publications, in reports like those from the <a href="https://www.ipcc.ch/">IPCC</a>, or in reports or websites from various governmental or non-governmental organizations. Few of them however are regularly updated and fully done reproducibly in the spirit of open science, where the latter would make it easier to achieve the former.</p>
<section id="polyclimate" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="polyclimate">Polyclimate</h3>
<p>The <em>Polyclimate</em> project is a place to think about how questions like the above could be approached using modern tools for collaboration, to discuss what are the barriers that so far prevented such collaboration from happening, and to hopefully kickstart some actual work on producing answers to these questions in a regularly updated, open, and inclusive way.</p>
<p>It is of course named after and inspired by the <a href="https://polymathprojects.org/">Polymath</a> project. In 2009 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timothy_Gowers">Timothy Gowers</a> asked in his blog the question:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><a href="https://gowers.wordpress.com/2009/01/27/is-massively-collaborative-mathematics-possible/">“Is massively collaborative mathematics possible?”</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The answer is of course yes, numerous publications and succesful proofs have emerged from the project and follow-ups. In the post he writes</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“I’ve been thinking of doing this for a long time.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So have I on doing this for some questions of climate science and when looking up whether someone had already used “Polyclimate” for this I was happily surprised to find some discussion in this <a href="https://judithcurry.com/2011/04/22/polyclimate/">blog</a>. This went apparently nowhere, and, to be clear, I am not interested in using “collective intelligence” or the “power of the internet” to “move forward on the climate debate”. Nonetheless, there are some interesting observations made, for example <a href="https://michaelnielsen.org/">Michael Nielsen</a> commented on the idea of <em>mass collaboration</em>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>A crucial question about mass collaboration is when problems can be attacked using mass collaboration, and when it will fail. I believe the key question is whether the community involved in the collaboration has a “shared praxis” or not. By this, I mean a powerful set of shared techniques and agreed-upon methods of reasoning which all participants agree to use.</p>
<p>[…]</p>
<p>For climate change the issue of a shared praxis seems complicated. I think it’s pretty near a dividing line. Reading online discussions of climate, it’s obvious that many people don’t even share the same basic modes of reasoning: what one person counts as “evidence” is ignored by others, basic standards of logic are outright ignored, and so on.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don’t think <em>massive</em> online collaboration is needed, but getting a number of researchers working together, which is larger than the usual teams collaborating on questions like the ones mentioned above could have tremendous benefits. There are many areas where finding the right specialist, for example with knowledge of some specific sector’s emission could be enabled by the internet much more likely than in traditional academic collaboration.</p>
<p>So this <em>Polyclimate</em> project is not about solving the “climate issue”. It is also not about the climate in urban systems which I discovered when searching for “polyclimate”:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Far more attached to the subject than Friedman, Schulze-Fielitz spent 20 years studying the air-conditioning of “urban systems.” His concept of “Polyclimate” went hand in hand with Raumstadt: to each activity its space and its climate. <span class="citation" data-cites="rouillard2018megaspace">(Rouillard 2018)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I hope <em>Polyclimate</em> can move forward the way in which researchers work together on some of the grunt work, producing basic data sets and indicators which are crucial for all of climate science but due to various reasons are not done continuously in a fully open, collaborative manner. Certainly, one can learn from the successes in online collaboration in Mathematics.</p>
</section>
<section id="polymath" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="polymath">Polymath</h3>
<p>An article in Nature (unfortunately paywalled, but available online at the <a href="https://www.michaelnielsen.org/papers/mcm.pdf">author’s website</a>) summarizes the Polymath story and lines out ideas for other disciplines:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The ‘Polymath Project’ proved that many minds can work together to solve difficult mathematical problems. <span class="citation" data-cites="Gowers_2009_bv7jtp">(Gowers and Nielsen 2009)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Building up a regularly updated global emissions or temperature dataset is of course quite different from finding a new proof, but there are many insights which can be adapted from the experiences of the Polymath projects.</p>
<p>In his book <em>Reinventing Discovery</em> <a href="https://michaelnielsen.org/">Michael Nielsen</a> argues that scientists are more likely to contribute to projects like Polymath or Galaxy Zoo where the final output is a classical output like a scientific paper compared to projects like GenBank or Wikipedia, where their expertise would be helpful as well but is not as incentivized <span class="citation" data-cites="nielsen2011reinventing">(p.9, Nielsen 2011)</span>. In Polymath, papers were published under the pseudonym D. H. J. Polymath. I believe that publishing under pseudonym or as a working group is a critical component in getting collaborative and repeatedly updated climate science to work.</p>
<p>There are many challenges for any such project and it is quite interesting to go back through the archives of Timothy Gower’s blog for the <a href="https://gowers.wordpress.com/category/polymath/">Polymath category</a>, read about the process, and find for example <a href="https://gowers.wordpress.com/2009/09/16/possible-future-polymath-projects/">discussions on thread depth</a> for the blog:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>On the Polymath blog, a very high level of threading is allowed, with the result that the order of comments is very different from their chronological order. This makes it substantially harder to check what has been added recently than it would be if there were no threading. It’s not impossible, since one has a list of recent comments, but it does reduce the feeling of a polymathematical thought process unfolding over time. I know that there is disagreement about this, but I am going back to the view that there should be no threading at all, though I might be ready to compromise and have threading down to depth 1, with the understanding that it should be used for brief local replies only.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="where-to-start" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="where-to-start">Where to start?</h3>
<p>Polymath started and happened to a large part on blogs. Looking for a place where I could start thinking about these questions I settled on <a href="https://github.com/polyclimate/">GitHub</a> and set up the blog you are reading now using <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a>. The latter enables inclusion of mathematical citation, code execution and citations. Comments are enabled in the blog using GitHub’s discussion feature through <a href="https://github.com/giscus/giscus/">Giscus</a>. Next to code hosting GitHub also offers Wikis, project management, issue tracking, and automated code pipelines, which means pretty much all potential ingredients for such collaborative work are there. Further, quite a few of the people I could imagine contributing to such efforts are already actively doing science in the open on GitHub, so if you have an account there you are ready to comment and contribute.</p>
<p>For any work done in public there are concerns about trolls, here GitHub has features for limiting interaction. As on most social platforms there can be difficulties for people from countries under <a href="https://docs.github.com/en/site-policy/other-site-policies/github-and-trade-controls">trade control regulations</a>, but for the usage of the free GitHub tools there should be no impediment in contributing. GitHub is a social platform, so it might be possible to recreate some of the fruitful collaboration which used to happen on sites like Twitter, where tagging the user account of a person knowledgeable on a niche topic could get them into a conversation and generate new insights.</p>
<p>With <a href="https://manubot.org/">Manubot</a> there is also a successful usage of GitHub as platform for collaborative science, developed during writing the Deep Review, a review article on deep learning in precision medicine <span class="citation" data-cites="Ching_2018_gddkhn Himmelstein_2019_c7np">(Ching et al. 2018; Himmelstein et al. 2019)</span>.</p>
<p>Challenges in online collaboration are of course partly technical, but I believe mostly social. Working in the open has benefits, but can also create new opportunities.</p>
<p>On the challenges with the research questions stated above, is it lack of funding for updates, which are just updates and not novel, shiny discoveries? Does the current academic system with its many short-term contracts disincentivize such work?</p>
<p>What questions in general could or should be approached in such a collaborative manner?</p>
<p>Leave your thoughts and ideas in the comments. (Sign up on GitHub if you haven’t already.)</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-Ching_2018_gddkhn" class="csl-entry">
Ching, Travers, Daniel S. Himmelstein, Brett K. Beaulieu-Jones, Alexandr A. Kalinin, Brian T. Do, Gregory P. Way, Enrico Ferrero, et al. 2018. <span>“Opportunities and Obstacles for Deep Learning in Biology and Medicine.”</span> <em>Journal of The Royal Society Interface</em> 15 (141): 20170387. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rsif.2017.0387">https://doi.org/10.1098/rsif.2017.0387</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Gowers_2009_bv7jtp" class="csl-entry">
Gowers, Timothy, and Michael Nielsen. 2009. <span>“Massively Collaborative Mathematics.”</span> <em>Nature</em> 461 (7266): 879–81. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/461879a">https://doi.org/10.1038/461879a</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Himmelstein_2019_c7np" class="csl-entry">
Himmelstein, Daniel S., Vincent Rubinetti, David R. Slochower, Dongbo Hu, Venkat S. Malladi, Casey S. Greene, and Anthony Gitter. 2019. <span>“Open Collaborative Writing with Manubot.”</span> Edited by Dina Schneidman-Duhovny. <em><span>PLOS</span> Computational Biology</em> 15 (6): e1007128. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007128">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007128</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-nielsen2011reinventing" class="csl-entry">
Nielsen, Michael. 2011. <em>Reinventing Discovery: The New Era of Networked Science</em>. Princeton University Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-rouillard2018megaspace" class="csl-entry">
Rouillard, Dominique. 2018. <span>“Megaspace Structure Yona Friedman and Eckhard Schulze–Fielitz.”</span> <em>Histories of Postwar Architecture</em>, no. 3: 3–18.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Polyclimate</category>
  <category>Polymath</category>
  <guid>https://polyclimate.org/posts/announcing-project-polyclimate/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2023 19:02:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
